So there's the simile of the wild
animal, but you can also think of it
like a uh childh.
Um
so I was just kind of thinking about
what it would mean to become a parent.
And I think whether you were planning on
it or not, if you do take on that role
of being a parent, your entire life
becomes the focal point becomes the fact
that you're a parent.
>> Mhm.
>> And I think that you would have to, at
least to me, it seems like you would
have to do that when it comes to
training the mind. You have to treat it
like this child. Um,
>> but the problem is you've been
neglecting it your whole life
>> and then
>> you kind of know at any point you could
just start neglecting it again and
>> outwardly it wouldn't have the same
consequences as if you just neglected a
child. >> But it's much worse actually.
>> But it's much worse actually.
>> Much worse.
>> Yeah. So that's
just for
trying to take on that practice on that
level where you're like, "No, this has
to be my main priority." Um,
at least to me, it seems like it's hard
to just kind of click that on and
>> stay with it. um
what es and flows with kind of bursts of
uh
inspiration, but I'm not sure if that um
necessarily corresponds to the actual
um
context of like really taking on the
role of being a parent to the mind.
>> Mhm. that I don't think that is
necessarily what comes and goes with
inspiration. >> Um,
>> Um,
>> but you mean the sense of being hatedful
about knowing that you're a parent?
>> Being hatedful about it? Yeah, I'd say
that. >> So, so why do you think that it uh kind
>> So, so why do you think that it uh kind
of fades?
>> Well, because you just you start
prioritizing yourself over the child
>> and and what is the necessary condition
to prioritize that?
I'm not sure if it would always
necessarily come down to the same thing,
but if just the child becomes too
demanding. >> Um but but like is it um
>> Um but but like is it um
is it just something that happens or is
it something that you fail to emphasize?
Well yeah it was it would definitely be
you actively
um
yeah so so if you take the example of a
parent like
what would they overlook because of
which they would I don't know start
going partying or
doing random things that are rooted in
neglect of their child
something that applies to them not only
to the child.
>> Well, the consequences of doing that.
>> Yeah. So, basically
what they themselves will have to put up
with as a result of
as a result of
neglecting the child. So, that's the
only reason why you would be able to get
careless because it feels like you can
get away with it,
but with the mind you can't. Like people
could hypothetically let's say you could
transfer the ownership of your child to
somebody else but with the mind you
can't. So if if you reflect every single time
So if if you reflect every single time
in the past where you were suffering why
was it
>> because of the mind. Mhm.
>> So each time you get careless if you
like that impulse can arise but the
thing is if you make the effort or not
to think about how that ends
to remember all the times in the past
where you were just trapped by this
incessant uh pressure
because precisely because of the same
choice that you're about to make now of
saying like no no it doesn't matter.
matter. I'll just go do something else
and worry about this child later. So,
every single time in the past, maybe it
wasn't that uh deliberate and explicit,
but that was the reason why you ended up
in those very painful internal
situations. >> And that doesn't that doesn't
>> And that doesn't that doesn't
necessarily mean like
um some intense experience of like total
despair. It could just be,
>> this is a question, like it it could
just be kind of a time where you find
yourself just not willing to do what you
know you should be doing.
>> Yeah. Like anything that feels like I
don't want to have this. It's that sense
of cuz you know there's suffering quote
unquote suffering that it's like
it's not really a problem. like you know
you're exercising for example
>> and it factually hurts
>> but uh it's not like something that as
as to say takes over your mind gets a
grip on your mind but then there are
other things that do it doesn't and it
doesn't matter how um yeah insignificant
they seem in their content that's not
the measure the measure is that grip on
the mind that they take where it's like
it's it's it becomes the center of your
experience And even if you don't want to have it
And even if you don't want to have it
and you want to think about something
else, it just kind of sits there keeps
obsessing you and even if it's like a
minor doubt about something, it doesn't
matter. The point is like that sense of
confinement, that is the suffering.
that is the suffering.
So every time you neglect your mind and
prioritize other stuff, that's what
you're walking towards. that state where
like it might be the tiniest thing but
the mind gets caught up in it like like
a like a I don't know thorn or
something. It's like just trying to
wrigle and left and right and it's just
getting wound up more. So that's the
pain that you subject yourself to. And
if you if you um think about like now
before you actually get caught up in
that you see oh how is it now? and you
realize like, oh yeah, I have the space
to kind of think about different things.
I I could choose to steer direction, but
you know that once you keep going there,
the direction of carelessness, that's
not going to be the case anymore. If you
recall your experiences in the past,
like >> you lose like you had um you had the
>> you lose like you had um you had the
control of the ship and you willingly
relinquish it.
And you do it because you don't clarify
sufficiently how that can never be good
because it's like you focus on these
secondary benefits
of whatever. failing to see that the
only way that something can feel
pleasant, the only way that something
can feel satis satisfying the way you
expect this thing to be is if the mind
is not wound up.
So that priority if you actually wanted
to be happy let's say by getting
something you want
you would have to remember that that
just won't come ever unless you keep the
mind in a good state.
So that that analogy you give of the you
of the steering wheel and you do have
control but certain directions you
won't. Is there anything about that
other than just your memory of having
steered this way before?
>> No, you can feel like you can feel it
right now. Let's say you take yourself
you you um find a situation where you're
not that pressured,
which is probably going to be most of
the time if you're keeping precepts and
you you reflect like right now
how there is that at least relative
openness of like you know there there isn't
of like you know there there isn't
something that's uh obsessing your mind
and demanding your attention
above everything else. So you actually
make effort to clarify like why can't
[clears throat] I maintain this state?
Why is it that when something comes up
and I have a view that it's better to
fix it and get that content that I want
rather than preserving the state which
is the only way that I can actually be
have the peace or satisfaction I'm
looking for. So it's that inversion
where you think that getting what you
want, avoiding what you don't want is
what's going to bring you that
satisfaction. Whereas the only way is to
maintain that state of openness of the
mind
and then doesn't matter what comes you
will have you will be sat you will not
be dissatisfied.
But that's something you have to reflect
on because that uh distortion of
prioritizing getting the things or
avoiding the bad things that is
beginningless. So it's it's it's not it's by no means
So it's it's it's not it's by no means
obvious that the priority the only
source of happiness is actually the
mind. It's not obvious at all.
But as you make effort to reflect on it
then because it is the nature of things
it will become clearer and clearer and
you will gain confidence in that fact.
So next time when the mind pressures you
with something that that feels like it's
the end of the world if you don't get it
and you feel that constriction coming
like starting to approach. If you have
clarified that sufficiently then you
will be able to say no wait this is a
trap and that's the right view. like
it's having that confidence, not being
able to doubt that uh you're moving in
the wrong direction. There is no
justification. There is no um real like
happy ending that's going to come from
you prioritizing anything over the mind.
Because whatever you're prioritizing,
you are still prioritizing the mind just
wrongly. >> Well, it comes first. It's still come
>> Well, it comes first. It's still come
first. So, it's like it's the imagine
you think that you can experience things
directly, but there's always that thing in
but there's always that thing in
between.
You think that you I can just That's
actually a perfect way of describing the
distortion. You think I can just have
this thing I want and just because I
have it I will be happy.
>> But you have absolutely no access. There
is not a single inch of that thing that
you can touch except through the mind. M
>> so that's why it's complet it makes
absolutely no sense to shift that order
because even if it feels like it's like
um like it can only ever be an ignorant
perception. So that's why the ignorance
is beginningless like it it makes
absolutely no sense. If if it was
something that you had decided to start
thinking you couldn't have because it
just doesn't make sense.
And then also you can take the times
when things weren't the way you wanted
but the mind was relatively open let's
say [clears throat] and you can see oh
yes actually like this is a direct
demonstration of how it is actually the
craving that's the problem.
Because there's always imperfections,
always things that are not as ideal.
And many of those times there will be
that mind in between that is actually
fine with it. And you can see, oh yeah,
actually this wasn't as much of a problem as it
this wasn't as much of a problem as it
would have been if the mind was
pressured.
cuz that can be hard to see that
literally anything that you're
even if it's like you're worried about
the practice and whether you'll succeed
and make progress and whatnot,
That's all still kind of obviously
um
the significance of that is kind of
defined by how the mind regards it.
>> Exactly. And then you would that's how
you would be misconceiving the practice.
You would be thinking like oh yeah it's
this stuff that I have to do.
>> It's about this thing.
>> Yeah. Whatever whatever it happens to be
it's this stuff over there.
Whereas uh it's the practice is to
purify that mind.
through which you're thinking about the
practice. >> So to to tame that you could say uh tame
>> So to to tame that you could say uh tame
the pain.
>> It's like that suta where it's the um
former prince who's out in the forest
saying, "Oh, this is happiness. This is
bliss." >> Like,
>> Like,
>> yeah. Yeah. If your mind
was just completely chill with the fact
that there are leopards and panthers
that might eat you the next second, it
wouldn't be a problem
>> cuz your mind is not
>> exactly
>> having issues with it.
>> Yeah. So, it's in a way it's obvious,
but see, when the when it's kind of in
the flesh
>> and there's that active impulse
[clears throat] to prioritize the the
situation, >> uh you kind of go with it. you you let
>> uh you kind of go with it. you you let
the emphasis drift away. Whereas if you
like actually made the effort to think
about it when it when it's in those
situations, um it's kind of going to be
against the grain. You're going to have
to be kind of fighting against that uh
irrational impulse to blame the
circumstances. And that's what people
don't do. Like it makes sense to them
that yes, to most people, I'm sure, that
the mind is the reason why they're happy
or sad,
>> but let's say you're in the middle of an
argument that feels like extremely
important and it's like the end of the
world if it doesn't go the way you want.
>> And then you don't want to think about
the fact that it's actually the mind
that makes things unpleasant
because it won't allow you to to double
down in this investment the way you want
to. It would kind of make the whole thing
It would kind of make the whole thing
seem pointless
>> and it is but that's the whole point
like you have to make the effort to
think about it because this ignorance is
not just like an abstract
uh state. It's an impulse. You don't
want to think about the way things are.
>> Yeah. It's it's like when you're Yeah.
kind of like you were saying the
argument like when you're in an argument
with somebody and you realize your point
is wrong but you don't want to Yeah.
>> admit it.
>> Yeah. It seems like
having the correct approach to the mind
is like constantly being wrong in an
argument that you're really invested in
winning. >> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> You have to admit it. Yes.
>> Um
as I remember in lay life um
somebody wanted to like quit smoking and
was asking about it and a friend had
said like
the most important thing is to let
yourself feel bad about it if you do it.
if you smoke
>> like when like you're not going to stop
smoking overnight unless you're you know
really serious and whatnot but
>> kind of in the meantime you have to
admit to yourself that it's not good
when you are making the decision to do
it and
in a way that's kind of
>> coming at the the root which it's always
like oh well it's okay this time
>> it's always going to manifest that way.
because it's that sense of uh not
wanting to feel guilty about something
that is actually against your welfare.
It's quite similar. Yeah. Like um not
wanting to feel the burden of um I
shouldn't be giving into this craving
like just even before you decide like
I'm actually not going to give in just
the fact of being aware that it's bad to
give in. So that's why uh um delusion is
actually the most fundamental of all the
three defilements.
Without delusion, the other ones cannot
exist [clears throat] because it's the
delusion that allows you to keep like
it's because you already decided
to not see it as a problem that you can
act out in in the form of greed or in
the form of aversion.
And then obviously the times where
you're doing something and you're like,
I shouldn't be doing this,
it's either
a it's not actually a problem and you're
kind of overdoing it or you just haven't
seen that it's a problem clearly enough.
>> Yeah. So how do you see that whether
it's a problem or not when in those
cases where it might be ambiguous? So
ask where is the pressure? Is the
pressure in continuing to do the thing
or is the pressure in me thinking about
the the the stuff that I shouldn't be
doing and the restraint and and the
>> kind of uh uh renunciation or whatever.
If if the pressure is in the second one,
then it it probably isn't the problem.
you just kind of um your mind just wants
to find an outlet for that pressure or
restlessness, something that it can
blame for like no I'm just restless and
I shouldn't be acting out of that
restlessness. So see that's another case
where you would be prioritizing
something over the mind.
like you might have all these ideas of
of sense of duty that oh I should be um
engaging in these behaviors and avoiding
these other ones as a goal for for like
for its own sake and you don't see that
actually why would I be doing that well
the only answer is because I want to
tame my mind okay so is that actually
going to tame my mind like is that
detracting from pressures that my mind
has or is that the pressure that my mind
has
Yeah. If you overlook that context of
why you're doing it
like of like the point of this is
training the mind.
>> Yeah. Then that's that's the whole about
the praasa.
>> Yeah. You're just falling into like
>> even for virtue sake.
>> Yeah. Even if it's the right behavior
and the right abstaining and the right
restraint, >> the fact that you're overlooking why you
>> the fact that you're overlooking why you
have to do it makes it inaccurate.
And it won't always be the right
restraint if it's sorry. It won't always
be the right restraint if you're not
keeping that priority.
>> No, like
>> because you will fall into like this.
>> Yeah.
>> I meant in the sense of like
[clears throat] um let's say it the
thing arises as if because obviously you
don't have an outside point of view.
>> So to you it will arise as if like oh
yes this is an intention to to keep the
precepts for example
>> an intention to factually do what I have
to do. So it will feel like it is the
right restraint even if afterwards you
can say like yeah that was kind of
distorted to some extent because of the
pressure >> to you that is the direction of the
>> to you that is the direction of the
restraint.
>> So uh you don't try to deny that you
just realize like wait no but I am I'm
not doing this because after I do this
some magical thing will happen and and
the pieces will come together or
something. The only reason that this
makes that there is any point to this is
because well when the mind has greed the
mind must not be allowed to act out of
greed. So have I seen the greed that I'm
trying to get rid of? Because yeah maybe
those behaviors will restrain something.
Uh, nobody says they won't, but it will
not actually succeed and it will not
actually tame those defilements unless
you're aware of what defilements you're
trying to get rid of by by let's say
abstaining by you know those all those
sutas like um
he would reflect
uh reflect according to the origin
reflect reflect the yono
and with that he would eat only for the
sake of sustaining ing this body.
So like you're not just taking on a a
sense of duty of oh you shouldn't eat
too much because you know that's bad for
the practice. You reflect you only so to
see like oh I actually I you can see the
pressure to eat for its own sake. You
can see the pressure to find safety in
food. You can see the pressure to to
just enjoy taste. And to that extent you
uh contradict it by eating only for the
sake of the uh maintenance of this body.
Which means in turn that if there is no
pressure to uh like uh enjoy the taste
for its own sake and and delight in that
then you don't need to like push through
this reflection.
You just stay aware that there is no
greed right now. For example,
there's that whole suta where the Buddha
says, "A monk who is wise engages in
difficult practice
when he sees that there is that there is
something to wear away through that
difficult practice. When that thing has
worn away, he does not engage in
difficult practice anymore.
So no like universal gutanga that you do
forever because it's like you know um a
good it's good period.
>> If you can't explain it then you're
probably doing for the wrong reason.
>> But you're you're just saying that even
in reference to a reflection
>> nobody would see
>> because because it is it is a kind of um
well burden that you're subjecting
yourself to.
>> So there has to be a reason. There has
to be a an awareness of there is a
defilement that I'm trying to restrain
with this. You're not just doing it
because >> you want to do it
>> you want to do it
>> cuz then that could be that restlessness
>> and then you're putting the mind second
>> and really you would only do it if you
didn't want to
>> basically
>> like you you there wouldn't be a sense
of duty about something like that. Yeah.
It would be something where you're like,
"Oh, I don't want to."
>> Well, the pressure the pressure would be
to to go with the flow of, let's say,
enjoying the taste
>> and you're going in the opposite
direction. So, that's the whole point of
that phrase against the grain.
>> So, if the grain is like, I want to
enjoy this. Well, the against the grain
is to reflect on why I shouldn't enjoy
this or reflect on something that at
least um puts that enjoyment second and
doesn't allow me to act towards it. Then
if the grain is like yeah I'm not even
thinking about the taste of the food
like it's not even crossing my mind but
the obsession now is I must engage in
this reflection
then if you do that now that's with the
drink
>> it means you've lost sight of what this
whole restraint is supposed
>> and you're not seeing the mind anymore.
Yeah.
So you will actually feel the tug of of
that uh defilement if you don't reflect.
You see like the mind wants to find some
other duty to latch on to some other
kind of
uh way to feel safe through that activ
um constant activity.
And then your reflection is why you
shouldn't engage in that. And that's now
against the grain.